<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "dtd/dblite.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % Symbols SYSTEM "Symbols.ent">
%Symbols;
]>
<!--
 Enter Glossary definitions in alphabetical Order!
 DocBook doesn't sort them automatically.
-->
<glossary id="Graph-glossary">
	<title>Glossary</title>
	<glossentry id="ComplexNumber">
		<glossterm>complex number</glossterm>
		<indexterm><primary>complex number</primary></indexterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>
				Complex numbers are a superset of real numbers. Complex numbers are two dimensional and is most often written
				on rectangular form as a+b&imag; where <parameter>a</parameter> is the real part and
				<parameter>b</parameter> is the imaginary part.
				The imaginary unit &imag; is defined as &imag;^2=-1.
				Complex numbers can also be shown on polar form as a&ang;&theta; where <parameter>a</parameter> is the absolute value of
				the number and &theta; is the angle of the number in radians or degrees.
			</para>
			<para>
				Complex numbers are used in the <guilabel>Evaluate</guilabel> dialog for standard functions and for graphing functions when
				<guilabel>Calculate with complex numbers</guilabel> is enabled under the <xref linkend="AxesDialogSettings"/> tab in the
				<guilabel>Edit axes</guilabel> dialog.
			</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry id="GraphElement">
		<glossterm>graph element</glossterm>
		<indexterm><primary>graph element</primary></indexterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>
				 A graph element is something that is shown in the coordinate system. This can be a function, point series, label, relation, etc.
				 The graph elements are also shown in the function list where they can be manipulated from the <guimenu>Function</guimenu> menu or the context menu.
			</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry id="FunctionList">
		<glossterm>function list</glossterm>
		<indexterm><primary>function list</primary></indexterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>
				The function list is shown in the left side of the main window. This list shows a list
				of all functions, tangents, point series, shadings and relations. When you want to manipulate
				an item, you first have to select it. The selected item is normally marked in blue, but it will
				be marked in gray when something other than the function list has focus. You can manipulate the selected element through
				the <guimenu>Function</guimenu> menu or through the context menu appearing when you <action>right click</action> on the element.
			</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry id="Integer">
		<glossterm>integer</glossterm>
		<indexterm><primary>integer</primary></indexterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>
				The set of numbers ...,-3,-2,-1,0,1,2,3,... is called integers and is a subset of the real numbers.
				A given integer n may be negative, zero or positive.
			</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry id="Legend">
		<glossterm>legend</glossterm>
		<indexterm><primary>legend</primary></indexterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>
				The legend is a box that per default is placed at the upper right corner of the graphing area, and shows a list of the plotted functions, tangents, shadings,
				and point series in the coordinate system. Select <guilabel>Show legend</guilabel> under <xref linkend="AxesDialogSettings" />
				in the <guilabel>Edit axes</guilabel> dialog to show the legend. <action>Right click</action> on an item in the function list and deselect
				<guimenuitem>Show in legend</guimenuitem> if you don't want the item shown in the legend.
				When editing an item you can enter the text to be shown in the legend.
				For functions and tangents the function equation will be shown if no legend text is entered.
			</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry id="NumericExpression">
		<glossterm>numeric expression</glossterm>
		<indexterm><primary>numeric expression</primary></indexterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>
				An expression that can be evaluated as a number is called a numeric expression.
				The expression can include any combination of numbers, constants, variables, operators and functions.
			</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry id="Radians">
		<glossterm>radians</glossterm>
		<indexterm><primary>radians</primary></indexterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>
				Radians are a way to describe the size of an angle similar to degrees, but radians are not a unit like degrees.
				The angle of a whole circle is 360&deg; or 2&pi; radians. An angle in radians can be converted to degrees by
				multiplying with 180&deg;/&pi;. An angle in degrees can be converted to radians by multiplying with &pi;/180&deg;.
				You can choose to use radians or degrees for trigonometric functions in the
				<guilabel>Edit axes</guilabel> dialog under the <xref linkend="AxesDialogSettings"/> tab.
			</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry id="RealNumber">
		<glossterm>real number</glossterm>
		<indexterm><primary>real number</primary></indexterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>
				A real number is on the form nnn.fffEeee where nnn is the whole number part that may be negative.
				fff is the fraction part that is separated from the integer part with a dot '.'.
				The fraction part is optional, but either the integer part or the fraction part must be there.
				E is the exponent separator and must be an 'E' in upper case. eee is the exponent optionally preceded by '-'.
				The exponent is only needed if the E is there. Notice that 5E8 is the same as 5*10^8.
			</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>
</glossary>
