<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "dtd/dblite.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % Symbols SYSTEM "Symbols.ent">
%Symbols;
]>
<section id="InsertRelationDialog">
	<?dbhh topicname="IDH_DIALOG_RELATION" topicid="20"?>
	<title>Insert relation</title>
	<indexterm><primary>relation</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>equation</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>equality</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>inequality</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>constraints</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>implicit function</primary></indexterm>
	<para>
		This dialog is used to insert a relation in the coordinate system.
		<quote>Relation</quote> is a common name for inequalities and equations, also known as implicit functions.
		To insert a relation you use the menu item <menuchoice><guimenu>Function</guimenu><guimenuitem>Insert relation...</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
		To change an existing relation, you first select it in the <glossterm>function list</glossterm> and use <menuchoice><guimenu>Function</guimenu><guimenuitem>Edit...</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
	</para>

  <graphic fileref="DialogRelation.png" align="center" scale="60"/>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Relation</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Here you enter the relation you want to graph.
					This must either be an equation or an inequality.
					<parameter>x</parameter> and <parameter>y</parameter> are used as the independent variables.
					An equation is a statement that one quantity equals another and the quantities must be separated by the = operator.
					For example the equation <literal>x^2 + y^2 = 25</literal> will plot a circle of radius 5.
				</para>
				<para>
					An inequality is a statement that one quantity is greater or less than another, and the quantities must be separated by one of the four operators: &lt;, >, &lt;=, >=.
					An inequality can for example be <literal>abs(x) + abs(y) &lt; 1</literal>.
					Two operators can be used to specify a range, for example <literal>y &lt; sin(x) &lt; 0.5</literal>.
				</para>
				<para>
					You can use the same operators and <link linkend="ListOfFunctions">built-in functions</link> as for plotting graphs of functions.
					In addition you can also create <link linkend="CustomFunctionsDialog">custom functions</link>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term>Constraints</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Here you can enter optional constraints, which can be any <glossterm>numeric expression</glossterm>.
					The relation will only be valid and plotted where the constraints are fulfilled, i.e. evaluates to a non-zero value.
					The constraints usually consist of a series of inequalities separated with the logical operators
					(<simplelist type="inline">
					  <member><function>and</function></member>
						<member><function>or</function></member>
						<member><function>xor</function></member>
					</simplelist>).
					As for the relation, <parameter>x</parameter> and <parameter>y</parameter> are used as the independent variables.
				</para>
				<para>
					For example if you have the relation <literal>x^2 + y^2 &lt; 25</literal>, which is a shaded circle,
					the constraints <literal>x > 0 and y &lt; 0</literal> will only show the part of the circle in the 4<superscript>th</superscript> quadrant.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term>Description</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Here you may enter a descriptive text to show in the <glossterm>legend</glossterm>.
					If this field is left empty, the relation and constraints will be shown in the legend.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term>Properties</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Here you may select a shading style for inequalities, color and width for equations.
					The shading <guilabel>Style</guilabel> is only used for inequalities and is ignored for equations.
					To see overlapping inequalities they must use different styles.
					The <guilabel>Width</guilabel> indicates the size of the line drawn for equations and the width of the border line for inequalities.
					For inequalities the width can be set to 0 to avoid drawing the border line.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
</section>
