<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "dtd/dblite.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % Symbols SYSTEM "Symbols.ent">
%Symbols;
]>
<section id="InsertTangentDialog">
	<?dbhh topicname="IDH_DIALOG_TANGENT" topicid="60"?>
	<title>Insert tangent/normal</title>
	<indexterm><primary>insert</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>tangent</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>standard function</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>parametric function</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>normal</primary></indexterm>
	<para>
		You can use the dialog below to insert or edit a tangent or normal to a function.
		To insert a new tangent or normal, you use <menuchoice><guimenu>Function</guimenu><guimenuitem>Insert tangent/normal...</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
		To change an existing tangent or normal, you first select it in the <glossterm>function list</glossterm> and use <menuchoice><guimenu>Function</guimenu><guimenuitem>Edit...</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
	</para>
	<para>
		A tangent is a straight line that touches the graph of the function at a given point without crossing it.
		The tangent may however cross the graph elsewhere.
		A normal is a straight line perpendicular to the graph of the function at a given point.
		If the item is a standard function the point is identified by the x-coordinate,
		while the point is identified from the independent t-parameter for parametric and polar functions.
	</para>

  <graphic fileref="DialogTangent.png" align="center" scale="60"/>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Argument range</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					You can choose an interval for the tangent/normal.
					<guilabel>From</guilabel> and <guilabel>To</guilabel> indicates the start and end of the interval.
					You can leave one or both of them blank to draw the graph from minus infinity to plus infinity.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term>Endpoints</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Here you can choose to show markers at the start and/or end of the interval.
					If no interval is specified, the markers will be shown at the edge of the graphing area.
					The default is not to show any markers.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term>Legend text</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Enter a description to show in the <glossterm>legend</glossterm>. If empty the function equation will be used.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term>Graph properties</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					You can choose between different line styles for which you want the tangent/normal to be drawn.
					You can choose between solid, dashed, dotted or a combination of these.
					You can also choose the width of the tangent/normal.
					The width is notified in screen pixels.
					There are also a lot of different colors you can choose between.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
</section>
