<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "dtd/dblite.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % Symbols SYSTEM "Symbols.ent">
%Symbols;
]>
<section id="InsertPointSeriesDialog">
	<?dbhh topicname="IDH_DIALOG_POINT_SERIES" topicid="120"?>
	<title>Insert point series</title>
	<indexterm><primary>insert</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>point series</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>markers</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>smooth line</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>trendline</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>interpolation</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>labels</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>error bars</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>arrow</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>import</primary></indexterm>
	<para>
		You can use the dialog below to add a series of points to the coordinate system.
		The points will be shown in the coordinate system in the graphing area as a series of markers.
		To insert a new point series, you use <menuchoice><guimenu>Function</guimenu><guimenuitem>Insert point series...</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
		To change an existing point series, you first select it in the <glossterm>function list</glossterm> and use <menuchoice><guimenu>Function</guimenu><guimenuitem>Edit...</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
	</para>

  <graphic fileref="DialogPoints.png" align="center" scale="80"/>

	<para>
		After adding a point series, you may add a <link linkend="InsertTrendlineDialog">trendline</link> which is the curve of best fit for the points.
	</para>
	<para>
		In the grid you can enter the x- and y-coordinates of the points.
		You may enter any number of points you want, but all points need both an x-coordinate and a y-coordinate.
	</para>
	<para>
		You can select some points and use the right click menu to copy them to another program.
		Likewise you may copy data from other programs like MS Word or MS Excel and paste them into this the grid in dialog.
	</para>
	<para>
		From the context menu, you can also choose to import data from a file.
		Graph can import text files with data separated by either tabs, commas or semicolons.
		The data will be placed at the position of the caret.
		This makes it possible to load data from more than one file, or to have x-coordinates in one file and y-coordinates in another file.
		In the usual case where you have all data in one file, you should make sure that the caret is located at the upper left cell before you import.
	</para>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Description</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					In the edit box at the top of the dialog, you can enter a name for the series, which will be shown in the <glossterm>legend</glossterm>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term>Coordinate type</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					You need to choose between the type of coordinates used for the points.
					<guilabel>Cartesian</guilabel> is used when you want to specify (x,y)-coordinates.
					<guilabel>Polar</guilabel> is used when you want to specify (&theta;,r)-coordinates,
					where <emphasis>&theta;</emphasis> is the angle and <emphasis>r</emphasis> is the distance from the origin.
					The angle <emphasis>&theta;</emphasis> is in <glossterm>radians</glossterm> or degrees depending on the current setting.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term>Marker</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					To the right you can choose between different types of markers.
					The style may be a circle, a square, a triangle, etc.
					You may also change the color and size of the markers.
					If the size is set to 0, neither markers nor error bars will be shown.
				</para>
				<para>
					Notice that if you select an arrow as marker, the arrow will be shown pointing tangential to the line at the point.
					The actual direction therefore depends on the <guilabel>Interpolation</guilabel> setting.
					The first point is never shown when the marker is an arrow.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term>Line</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					It is possible to draw lines between the markers.
					The line will always be drawn between points in the same order they appear in the grid.
					You can choose between different styles, colors and widths for the lines.
					You can also choose to draw no line at all.
				</para>
				<para>
					You can choose between four types of interpolation: <guilabel>Linear</guilabel> will draw straight lines between the markers.
					<guilabel>1D cubic spline</guilabel> will draw a <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cubic_splines">natural cubic spline</ulink>,
					which is a nice smooth line connecting all the points sorted by the x-coordinate with 3<superscript>rd</superscript> degree polynomials.
					<guilabel>2D cubic spline</guilabel> will draw a smooth cubic spline through all points in order.
					<guilabel>Half cosine</guilabel> will draw half cosine curves between the points,
					which might not look as smooth as the cubic splines but they never undershoot/overshoot like the cubic splines can do.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term>Labels</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Put a check in <guilabel>Show coordinates</guilabel> to show Cartesian or polar coordinates at each point.
					You may use the <guibutton><inlinegraphic fileref="Font.png" scale="60"/></guibutton>
					button to change the font, and the drop down box to select whether the labels are shown over, below, to the left or to the right of the points.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term>Error bars</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Here you can choose to show horizontal or vertical error bars, also known as uncertainty bars.
					They are shown as thin bars at each point in the point series indicating the uncertainty of the point.
					There are three ways to indicate the size of the error bars:
					<guilabel>Fixed</guilabel> is used to specify that all points have the same uncertainty.
					<guilabel>Relative</guilabel> is used to specify a percentage of the x- or y-coordinate for each point as uncertainty.
					<guilabel>Custom</guilabel> will add an extra column to the table where you may specify a different uncertainty value for each point.
					All uncertainties are &plusmn;values. Custom Y-errors are also used to weight the points when creating trendlines.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
</section>
