<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "dtd/dblite.dtd">
<chapter id="OLE">
	<title>OLE server/client</title>
	<indexterm><primary><acronym>OLE (Object Linking and Embedding)</acronym></primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary><acronym>COM (Component Object Model)</acronym></primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>linking</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>embedded</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>automation</primary></indexterm>
	<simplesect renderas="sect2">
		<title>OLE server</title>
		<para>
			Graph has been implemented as an OLE (Object Linking and Embedding) server, which means that Graph objects can be placed (embedded) into an OLE client.
			Many applications can work as OLE clients, for example Microsoft Word.
		</para>
		<para>
			You can use
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Copy image</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>
			in Graph to copy the current content to the clipboard.
			Afterwards you can select	<guimenuitem>Paste</guimenuitem>
			in Word (or similar in another OLE client) to insert the Graph object from the clipboard.
			When you double click on the object a new instance of Graph will start where you can edit the object.
			If you don't want to paste the data as a Graph object into Word, you can use
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>Paste</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Paste Special...</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>
			in Word to paste as a picture instead.
		</para>
		<para>
			You may create a new Graph object in Word by choosing
		  <guimenuitem>Object</guimenuitem>
			in the toolbar and selecting <guilabel>Graph system</guilabel> as <guilabel>Object type</guilabel>.
			The same dialog can be used to create an embedded Graph object from an existing grf-file.
			If you select <guilabel>Link to file</guilabel>, you will get a linked object instead of an embedded object.
			This way all changes to the object will be reflected in the original grf-file.
			If the grf-file is not available you will not be able to edit the object, but you can still see the image in Word.
		</para>
		<para>
			To edit a Graph object you must have Graph installed on the system.
			If Graph is not installed you will still be able to see the image but not edit it.
		</para>
	</simplesect>

	<simplesect renderas="sect2">
		<title>OLE client</title>
		<para>
			Graph can work as an OLE client as a text label in Graph is an OLE container.
			This means that you can paste images and OLE objects into the editor used to add labels.
			As in any other OLE container you can edit the object by double clicking on it.
			From the context menu you can use <guimenuitem>Insert object...</guimenuitem> to create a new OLE object in the label.
			The same dialog can be used to create an object from a file.
			You can for example insert an image file this way.
			To edit an OLE object the server must be installed on the system, else you will only be able to see object but not edit it.
		</para>
	</simplesect>
</chapter>
